RUAM P. F. A. PIMENTEL

I have experience conducting research on psychological assessment and currently I am focusing on how to improve and have new approaches to the Rorschach Method. I am also intrigued by the potential of multimethod psychological measures and how different mental states effect perception.

My current goal is to get more experience with Natural Language Processing and apply it to psychological assessment methods, specifically, to the Rorschach task.



EDUCATION

2024 2019

Ph.D. Candidate, Psychology, Quantitative Psychology (Minor)

University of Toledo

Toledo, OH (USA)

- · Qualifying Exam and Dissertation: Systematic review and meta-analyses of malingering on the Rorschach task
- Potential depressive indicators on the Rorschach task
- · Comparison of remote and in-person administration of the Rorschach task
- Development of an autonomous app for the Rorschach task

2019 2018

M.Sc., Psychology, Psychological Assessment

Universidade São Francisco

◆ Campinas, SP (Brazil)

- Thesis: Relation between R-PAS and BFI2 moderate by R-PAS selfperception indicators
- Experience as a psychologist conducting Therapeutic Assessment

2019 2018

Specialization in Neuroscience (300 hrs)

Universidade Federal de São Paulo

Santos, SP (Brazil)

• Thesis: Biomarkers of Borderline Personality Disorder: A Literature Review

2017 2012

B.S., Psychology

CEULP/ULBRA

Palmas, TO (Brazil)

- Thesis: The Effect of Valence on Source Memory in the Elderly
- In Brazil, we also receive practical training during undergrad. Hence, I practiced (e.g., externship and internship), under supervision, in the following areas: (1) Clinical Therapy (600+ hrs); (2) Psychological assessment (250+ hrs); (3) Neuropsychological assessment (250+ hrs); (4) Health Psychology in the department of neurosurgery of a public hospital (150+). Across all these areas, I've worked with 60+ patients.

View this CV online with links at ruampimentel.aithub.io/ Pimentel_CV/cv.html

CONTACT

- ▼ ruampimentel@gmail.com
- github.com/ruampimentel
- **P** ruampimentel.me

RELEVANT SKILLS

Data Analysis

Statistics, Psychometrics Data Visualization Structural Equation Modeling Machine Learning Models

Tech

R, Rstudio git, GitHub, SQL MPlus, SPSS Some Python

LANGUAGE

Portuguese (Native) Italian

Made with the R package pagedown. The source code is available on github.com/ruampimentel/ Pimentel_CV. Last updated on 2023-03-18.

☐ RELEVANT COURSES AND WORKSHOPS

Current 2016

Rorschach Courses and Workshops

- · Viglione, D. J. (2023, January). R-PAS Coding Solutions [8h Workshop]. www.r-pas.org
- Meyer, G. J., & Mihura, J. L. (2021). Introduction to R-PAS: Rationale, Administration, Coding, and Interpretation [25h Workshop].
- · Meyer, G. J., & Mihura, J. L. (2020). Introduction to R-PAS: Rationale, Administration, Coding, and Interpretation [25h Workshop].
- · Mihura, J. L., & Meyer, G. J. (2018a, June). Rorschach Performance Assessment System (R-PAS): Forensic, educacional and clinical application [8h Workshop].
- · Mihura, J. L., & Meyer, G. J. (2018b, June). Rorschach Performance Assessment System (R-PAS): Instrumentalizing trainers and researchers [8h Workshop1.
- Resende, A. C. (2018a). Rorschach Basic Course (Comprehensive System) [40h course].
- Resende, A. C. (2018b). Rorschach Intermediate Course (Comprehensive System) [40h course].
- · Resende, A. C. (2017). Rorschach Advanced Course (Comprehensive System) [40h course].

Current 2018

Data Analysis (e.g., Psychometrics, Stats, and R)

- · Meyer, G. J. (2022). Psychometrics [Full Ph.D. course].
- Elhai, J. D. (2021). Data Analysis with R [Full Ph.D. course].
- Elhai, J. D. (2020). Structural Equation Modeling [Full Ph.D. course].
- · Khuder, S. (2020). Categorical Data Analysis in R [Full Ph.D. course].
- · Valentini, F. (2019). Factor Analysis and Structural Equation Modeling (Pt: Análise Fatorial e Modelagem de Equações Estruturais) [Full M.Sc. course].
- · Hauck Filho, N. (2019). Psychometrics (Pt: Psicometria) [Full M.Sc. course].
- Eremenko, K. (2018). R Programing A-Z: R for data science with real exercises! [10.5h online course].
- Primi, R. (2018). Data Science with R (Pt: Ciência de Dados com o R) [Full M.Sc. course].
- Machado, W. de L. (2018). Scale construction using non-parametric item response theory (pt: Construção de escalas usando teoria de resposta ao item não-paramétrica) [4h Workshop].

2017

Advanced Report Writing for Forensic, Psychological, and Neuropsychological Assessment (12h)

Goiano Institute of Psychological Assessment, IGAP

Goiânia, Goiás (Brazil)

• (Portuguese course name: Curso Perícia, Laudos & Pareceres Psicológicos)

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Current | 2021

Normative Data Collection Coordinator (Research Assistant)

Rorschach Perfomance Assessment System (R-PAS)

- Manage and coordinate international data collection efforts across 20+ countries
- Develop and distribute training materials and resources for data collectors, ensuring they are properly equipped and informed to carry out their tasks effectively.
- Conduct training sessions and study groups for data collectors, focusing on the proper use of the R-PAS.
- Assess and measure the proficiency level of data collectors to ensure accuracy and consistency in data collection processes.

Current | 2019

Psychological Assessment Lab

The University of Toledo

▼ Toledo, OH (USA)

- · Primary lab project: Administering R-PAS remotely
- Organizing data collection material and research workflow by integrating multiple sources of information (e.g., Qualtrics, Inquisit, Excel, R-PAS).
- · Training and coordinating team members.
- · Present lab studies at conferences

Work Education for Health Program

2023 | 2020

Translation and Adaptation of the Personality Assessment Inventory to Portuguese (Research Assistant)

- · Organize and clean datasets using R
- · Organize and clean items for translation
- Backtranslation (Portuguese to English)
- $\boldsymbol{\cdot}$ Run psychometrics (e.g., internal consistency, validity studies, norms) using R

2019 | 2018

Psychological Assessment in Mental Health Lab (LAPSaM)

Universidade São Francisco

• Campinas, SP (Brazil)

- $\boldsymbol{\cdot}$ Provide feedback and ideas to other members project (weekly meetings)
- Collaborate with other members' project being a second R-PAS coder to check reliability of their data
- Conduct Therapeutic Assessment in a few patients and discuss them with members.
- Discuss othe Therapeutic Assessment cases with members.
- Present lab studies at conferences

2015

Mental health and internet research

· Taxonomical research in a mental health site

2014

Physiotherapy and cognition research

CEULP/ULBRA

Palmas, TO (Brazil)

- \cdot Research in quality of life and attention in elderly and adults using kinect
- · Collect data administering cognitive measures in participant
- Writing a paper on the importance of heart rate variability for some aspects of cognition
- Presenting lab projects in conferences

♣☐ TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Current | 2020

Teaching Assistant

Rorschach Perfomance Assessment System (R-PAS)

• 2020 & 2021 - Introduction to R-PAS: Rationale, Administration, Coding, and Interpretation

Current | 2019

Teaching Assistant

The University of Toledo

▼ Toledo, OH (USA)

- 2021 Quantitative Methods in Psychology I (graduate level)
- · 2021 Statistical Methods (undergrad level)
- · 2020 Personality and Individual Differences (undergrad level)
- · 2020 Statistical Methods (undergrad level)
- 2020 Quantitative Methods in Psychology II (graduate level)
- 2019 Introduction to Psychology (undergrad level)

Workshop (Co)Instructor

- · Rorschach Performance Assessment System Basics (8 hrs Hogrefe Brazil)
- Rorschach Performance Assessment System Intermediate (12 hrs Hogrefe Brazil)

Guest Lecturer

- Personality and Culture
- Talk on Importance of multimethods on Psychological Assessment (2x)
- · Overview and introduction to Therapeutic Assessment
- · Overview and introduction to R-PAS (3x)

2019 | 2018

Teaching Assistant

Universidade São Francisco

- Thesis advising I (for undegrad)
- Thesis advising II (for undergrad)

2017 | 2014

Teaching Assistant

CEULP/ULBRA

- · Morphophysiology and human behavior
- Methods of psychological assessment
- · Psychological assessment
- Neuropsychological assessment

I firmly believe that education is a powerful tool for creating positive change in the world. My experience so far has primarily been in practical applications, and I always strive to encourage my students to go beyond what is taught in the classroom and learn for themselves.



Pianowski, G.; Giromini, L.; Pimentel, R. P. F. A.; Gonçalves, A. P.; Machado, G. M.; Hosseininasab, A.; Alghraibeh, A. M.; Brusadelli, E.; Rooney, E. A.; Colombarolli, Maíra S.; Tajamolian, M.; Herzog, N. K.; Rusconi, P.; Kelly, P.; Zare, S.; Ales, F.; Pignolo, C.; Andò, A.; Zennaro, A.; D. Girolamo, M. & F. Carvalho, L. 2022. Cross-cultural investigation from nine countries on the associations of antisocial traits and the WHO 's containment measures for the COVID -19 pandemic. Scandinavian Journal of Psychology. DOI: 10.1111/sjop.12869. .

Gonçalves, A. P.; Pimentel, R. P. F. A. & Carvalho, L. D. F. 2020. Funcionamento patológico da personalidade para predição da depressão, qualidade de vida e esperança. Interação em Psicologia. DOI: 10.5380/psi.v24i1.62784. 24 (1).

Brandão, P. S.; Neto, I. V. S.; Rauber, S. B.; Pimentel, R. P. F. A.; Zukowski, M. S.; Fagundes, F. & Campbell, C. S. G. 2017. Impacto de Exergames na qualidade de vida de idosos. Fisioterapia Brasil. DOI: 10.33233/fb.v18i3.1058. 18 (3).



CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS

O'Donoghue, E.; Pimentel, R. P. F. A. & Meyer, G. J. 2022-07-13. Assessing Potential R-PAS Score Differences for Inperson and Remote Administration. [Conference Symposium]. XXIII congress of the International Society for the Rorschach and Projective Methods - 2022. Geneva.

Pimentel, R. P. F. A. & Meyer, G. J. 2022-07-13. Rorschach and Depressive Behaviors: Potential depressive related behaviors discriminating patients with and without depressive symptoms and controls. [Conference Symposium]. XXIII congress of the International Society for the Rorschach and Projective Methods - 2022. Geneva.

Meyer, G. J.: Pimentel, R. P. F. A. & Pianowski, G. 2022-05-13. Avancos digitais na aplicação do teste de Rorschach: Desenvolvimento do aplicativo de administração do R-PAS (Digital advances in the administration of the Rorschach test: Development of the R-PAS administration app). [Coordenated Session]. X Congresso da ASBRo (X ASBRo Congress). Online.

Pimentel, R. P. F. A.; Meyer, G. J. & Pianowski, G. 2022-05-13. Avanços digitais na aplicação do teste de Rorschach: Uso do aplicativo de administração do R-PAS (Digital advances in the administration of the Rorschach test: Use of the R-PAS administration app). [Coordenated Session]. X Congresso da ASBRo (X ASBRo Congress). Online.

Pianowski, G.; Meyer, G. J. & Pimentel, R. P. F. A. 2022-03-13. Aplicativo de administração remota do R-PAS: Dados preliminares de equivalência (R-PAS Remote Administration Application: Preliminary equivalence data). [Coordenated Session]. X Congresso da ASBRo (X ASBRo Congress). Online.

O'Donoghue, E. M.; Meyer, G. J.; Pimentel, R. P. F. A. & Mihura, J. L. 2022-03-12. Assessing Potential R-PAS Score Differences for In-Person and Remote Administration. [Conference Symposium]. 2022 Society for Personality Assessment Convention. Chicago.

Pimentel, R. P. F. A.; Kiss, A. B.; Mihura, J. L.; Meyer, G. J.; Kletzka, N. & Eblin, J. J. 2022-03-11. Comparing committed Forensic Inpatients to Non-Patients Instructed to Malinger Insanity of Not Using Scores from the Rorschach task and Self-report. [Conference Symposium]. 2022 Society for Personality Assessment Convention. Chicago.

Pimentel, R. P. F. A.; Meyer, G. J.; Guimarães-Neto, A.; Vieira, P. G. & Villemor-Amaral, A. E. 2022-03-11. Comparing Patients with Schizophrenia to Non-Patients Instructed to Malinger Insanity or Not Using Scores from the Rorschach Task and Self-Report. [Conference Symposium]. 2022 Society for Personality Assessment Convention. Chicago.

My main responsibility as coauthor involved data collection, data cleaning, data analysis, data visualization, or writing up results.

I have presented most of my work at conferences so far. I am now transitioning to publishing it more in journals rather than just in conferences.

Pimentel, R. P. F. A. 2021-10-23. *Opções e Desafios da pesquisa com Testes de Perfomance em tempos pandêmicos (Options and Challenges of Research with Performance Tests in Pandemic Times*). [guest speaker]. ASBRo monthly meeting. Online.

Herzog, N. K.; **Pimentel**, R. P. F. A. & R. 2021-10. Beyond the 'Mask Wars': Cross-national comparison of health protective behaviors, government compliance, and empathy. [Conference Presentation]. 2021 APHA Annual Meeting.

Pimentel, R. P. F. A. & Villemor-Amaral, A. E. 2021-10. *The Pfister colored pyramid test and its use in C/TA*. [Paper Presentation]. CTAC – Collaborative/Therapeutic Assessment Conference 2021. Online.

Pimentel, R. P. F. A.; Herzog, K. H. & Rooney, E. 2021-10. *One for All and All for One: Culture, Personality, and Governmental Policies Predicting Mask-Wearing in an International Sample*. [Paper Presentation]. 2021 APHA Annual Meeting. Online.

Pianowski, G.; **Pimentel**, R. P. F. A.; Gomes, G. V. A. & Salgado, M. 2021-09. *Sistema de Avaliação por Performance no Rorschach Itermediário: Administração e Codifição (Intermediate Rorschach Performance Assessment System: Administration and Coding)*. [12hrs Workshop]. Hogrefe Brazil. Online.

Pianowski, G. & **Pimentel**, R. P. F. A. 2020-10-31. *Sistema de Avaliação por Performance no Rorschach: Uma Breve Introdução ao R-PAS (Rorschach Perfomance Assessment System: A brief introduction to R-PAS)*. [8hrs Workshop]. Hogrefe Brazil. Online.

CONFERENCE PAPER

Pimentel, R. P. F. A. & Meyer, G. J. 2020. *Sentiment Analysis in Rorschach responses [e-poster for online conference]*. Brazilian Institute of Psychological Assessment (Instituto Brasileiro de Avaliação Psicológica). Online.

Pimentel, R. P. F. A. & Tavares, M. D. 2018. *The influence of emotional valence over Source Memory in Aging [Paper Presentation]*. Presented at XLI annual meeting of the Brazilian Society of Neuroscience and Behavior (SBNeC; Sociedade Brasileira de Neurociência e Comportamento).

Pimentel, R. P. F. A. & Villemor-Amaral, A. E. 2018. *Relation between R-PAS and BFI2 moderate by R-PAS self-perception indicators: preliminary studies [Paper presentation]*. V Brazilian Congress of Psychology: Science and Profession (CBP; Congresso Brasileiro de Psicologia). São Paulo, Brazil.

Pimentel, R. P. F. A. & Tavares, M. D. 2016. What do we know about the Source Memory in Aging? A review [Paper presentation]. Presented at XV Brazilian Congress of the Brazilian Society of Neuropsychology (SBP; Sociedade Brasileira de Psicologia).. Brasília, Brazil.

UNPUBLISHED WORK

Pimentel, R. P. F. A.; Pianowski, G.; Kline, J. S. & Meyer, G. J. 2023. *Potential depressive-related Rorschach behaviors discriminating patients with and without depressive symptoms and controls*. [Manuscript submitted for publication]. Department of Psychology, University of Toledo.

Kiss, A.; Mihura, J.L.; Meyer, G. J.; **Pimentel**, R. P. F. A. & Klezka, N. 2022. *Comparing committed forensic inpatients to nonpatients instructed to malinger insanity or not using scores from the Rorschach task and self-report*. [Manuscript submitted for publication]. Department of Psychology, University of Toledo.

My works that have not been published include manuscripts that are still in preparation and guidelines for coding new behaviors on the Rorschach task. These guidelines were used in some of my published work, but never published independently.

Pimentel, R. P. F. A.; Meyer, G. J. & Mihura, J. L. 2022. *Malingering severe psychopathology on the Rorschach task: Systematic review and meta-analysis*. [Manuscript in preparation]. Department of Psychology, University of Toledo.

Meyer, G. J.; Pianowski, G.; **Pimentel**, R. P. F. A. & Zuanazzi, A. C. 2021. *Pleasant or Appealing Expressions (PAE)*. [Unpublished scoring manual]. Department of Psychology, University of Toledo.

Meyer, G. J.; **Pimentel**, R. P. F. A.; Pianowski, G. & Vanhoyland, M. 2021. *Coding criteria for Breaking the Card Boundary (BCB)*. [Unpublished scoring manual]. Department of Psychology, University of Toledo.

Meyer, G. J.; Zuanazzi, A. C.; Gonçalves, A. P.; Pianowski, G. & **Pimentel**, R. P. F. A. 2021. *Self-Critical and Helpless Reassurance Seeking Depressive Behavior Expressed During the Rorschach Task (SCHB)*. [Unpublished scoring manual]. Department of Psychology, University of Toledo.

MISCELLANEOUS

Current | 2020

Webmaster

Psychological Assessment Lab of the Department of Psychology

- · Reorganize the structure of the lab online pages
- · Update the lab online pages

Favorite R Packages

- tidyverse (e.g., dplyr, tidyr, forcats, stringr, ggplot2, purrr)
- psych, rstatix, lavaan, easystats (e.g., report, see, correlation, effectsize, perfomance, parameter, modelbased)
- tidymodels (e.g., rsample, recipes, parsnip, tune, yardstick)

Tech in general

I developed experience over the years through practical applications and courses

- Data Analysis: R, SPSS, G*Power, MPlus, SAS, Python (basics), JASP, Jamovi
- Microsoft Office (e.g., Word, Excel, PowerPoint, Outlook, Publisher, Access, OneDrive, Teams)
- Google Workspace (e.g., Docs, Sheets, Slides, Calendar, Sites, Forms, Youtube)
- $\bullet \ \, \text{Survey, Experiment and Course Designs (Qualtrics, Inquisit, Learn worlds)}$
- $\boldsymbol{\cdot}$ Project management tools (e.g., Notion, Trello, Smartsheet, Toogl, github projects)
- Note taking apps (Obsidian, Markdown files)
- Others: Rerefence managers (Zotero, End Note, Mendley); Figma (interface design); DaVinci Resolve (Video Editor); Audio editors (Reaper, Audacity, Garage Band); Send in Blue (email marketing), Spark (email manager), Fantastical (calendar manager)

Musician

Instruments that I play listed by order of proficiency:

- · Piano, guitar & bass
- · Ukulele & harmonica
- · Violin, cello & flute